<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">Sumedh Joshi</title>
<generator uri="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="" />
<updated>2015-07-21T14:32:02-05:00</updated>
<id>/</id>
<author>
  <name>Sumedh Joshi</name>
  <uri>/</uri>
  <email>sumedh.m.joshi@gmail.com</email>
</author>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[When Do I Write Code?]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/programming/when-do-i-write-code/" />
  <id>/programming/when-do-i-write-code</id>
  <published>2015-07-21T12:12:22-05:00</published>
  <updated>2015-07-21T12:12:22-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Sumedh Joshi</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>sumedh.m.joshi@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;I use &lt;a href=&quot;https://mercurial.selenic.com/&quot;&gt;Mercurial&lt;/a&gt; as a version control system for part of my dissertation work, the development of a finite element code.  Besides being easy to use, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bitbucket.org&quot;&gt;hosted online&lt;/a&gt;, and useful, it also lets me evaluate how/when I make changes to my code.  By looking at the number of changes I make per day/month/whatever, I can get a rough estimate of when I’m working, when I’m not, and what my work habits are in general.  In Mercurial, this is really easy to do since all change logs can be accessed via command line with&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;hg log -v &amp;gt; logs.txt&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then just use your favorite text parser to sort the straightforward logs.txt file which contains records of each change in a standardized format, e.g.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  changeset:   59:783a1a00679c0i
  user:        Sumedh Joshi &amp;lt;smj96@cornell.edu&amp;gt;
  date:        Tue Jan 07 08:35:49 2014 -0500
  files:       apply_laplacian.f90
  description:
  Topic: Fixed minor error in Laplacian.
  Description:
  * Factor of two error incorrect in the Laplacian.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve made about 600 changes to my repository over the last 1.5 years, and they tell me something about how I work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;changes-by-day-and-month&quot;&gt;Changes by day and month.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I just sorted all of my changes by month and day (shown in the two pie charts below).  I work, predictably, little on the weekends, and least of all on Saturdays, which are reserved for college football.  Tuesday is my most productive day, slightly edging out Mondays.  Wednesdays are my least productive weekday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;half&quot;&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
   &lt;a href=&quot;/images/sumedh_commits_by_day.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;50%&quot; src=&quot;/images/sumedh_commits_by_day.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
   &lt;a href=&quot;/images/sumedh_commits_by_month.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;50%&quot; src=&quot;/images/sumedh_commits_by_month.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
   &lt;figcaption&gt; Left: The number of changes per day over the last year.  Right: The number of changes per month over the last year. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Month-wise, I am at my most productive in the winter months: January, December, and February in that order.  Probably this just because over the last 1.5 years these months have occured twice, but so have several other months which are not as productive.  My best explanation is that these months have bad weather so I probably spend more time inside, and also there isn’t any major team I am a fan of that is in season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By far my least productive months are August (football), September (football), and May (NBA playoffs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;changes-by-hour-of-day&quot;&gt;Changes by hour of day.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of perks of being a graduate student is that you don’t have to work in the middle of the day.  These are great times to run errands, work out at an empty gym, go play golf, whatever.  Looking at my changes logs over a 24-hour day (below bar graph) it’s clear that 1. I am not a morning person and 2. I take full advantage of my schedule’s flexibility by working evenings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
   &lt;a href=&quot;/images/sumedh_commits_by_hour.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;80%&quot; src=&quot;/images/sumedh_commits_by_hour.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
   &lt;figcaption&gt; The number of changes per hour of the day. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of my changes (like, the vast majority of them), occur between noon and midnight, with a slight peak at 7pm.  I’ve only had a handful of changes between 7-9am, and if I was working before then, it’s probably just because I was up from the night before.  My schedule has gotten more regular since my fiancee started working so I expect this to change over the next year.  It’ll be fun to look back on this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-many-changes-on-an-average-day-of-work&quot;&gt;How many changes on an average day of work?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the 450 or so days I’ve had this repository I’ve made 600 or so changes, which averages to a little over 1 per day.  But, if I had to guess, the vast majority of days I make no changes at all, and on days that I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; make changes I make way more than 1.  To see if my guess was correct, I made a histogram of number of changes I make on days that I actually worked (shown below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
   &lt;a href=&quot;/images/sumedh_commits_per_day_of_work.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;80%&quot; src=&quot;/images/sumedh_commits_per_day_of_work.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
   &lt;figcaption&gt; The number of changes I make on a day in which I actually work.  April 2nd, 2014: 28 changes.  Never forget.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I’m only sort of right.  On the average day I worked, I made about 5 code changes.  The distribution is very non-symmetric (naturally since you can’t have &lt;em&gt;negative&lt;/em&gt; changes) and looks basically like a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rayleigh_distribution&quot;&gt;Rayleigh distribution&lt;/a&gt;.  There is still a large chunk of days in which I made just 1 or 2 changes which is surprising since I don’t remember those days, but perhaps also unsurprising since… why would I?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I don’t know what got into me on April 2nd of last year, but I checked in 28 changes in a single 24-hour period.  This is over 30 times my daily average over the last year.  Probably some combination of my impending dissertation proposal and the lack of any sort of football motivated me to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To conclude: today is Tuesday, it is July, and it is about 2:30pm.  By historical measures, I should be working diligently instead of writing this post, which is the only commit I’m making to any repository today.&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/programming/when-do-i-write-code/&quot;&gt;When Do I Write Code?&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Sumedh Joshi at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Sumedh Joshi&lt;/a&gt; on July 21, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Google PageRank, NCAA Football, and Luck]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/football/google-pagerank-and-ncaa-football/" />
  <id>/football/google-pagerank-and-ncaa-football</id>
  <published>2015-07-03T03:00:45-05:00</published>
  <updated>2015-07-03T03:00:45-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Sumedh Joshi</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>sumedh.m.joshi@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;h2 id=&quot;graph-of-sports-leagues&quot;&gt;Graph of sports leagues&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think of sports teams as nodes (vertices) and games between teams as edges between the nodes, professional sports leagues have very different characters as graphs.  Most leagues are divided into divisions, or conferences, and so the graphs tend to have clusters within a division, and fewer edges between divisions.  All the graphs are connected, and some, like the one of the NBA, are even complete.  Usually, the sports leagues are divided into subgraphs that are themselves complete; for example Major League Baseball is divided into the American League and National League.  Within each League, all teams play each other, and teams have a limited set of games against teams in the other league (so-called interleague play).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The graphs of the major American sports leagues are characterized in the table below.  &lt;em&gt;Nodes&lt;/em&gt; means teams, &lt;em&gt;degree&lt;/em&gt; means games, and &lt;em&gt;complete sub-graphs&lt;/em&gt; means the number of divisions/conferences/etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;League&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;# of Nodes&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Degree of each node&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;# of Complete Sub-Graphs&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;NBA&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;30&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;82&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;MLB&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;32&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;162&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;NFL&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;32&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;16&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;Complete sub-graph&lt;/em&gt; is a term I’m using sort of heuristically here; every graph has lots of complete subgraphs of small size; I mean complete sub-graph of conference/division size.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-graph-of-college-football&quot;&gt;The graph of college football&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The graph of college football is very different from the ones described above.  This is because a college football team will only play about 12 games in a season, and there is something like 130 college football teams.  There is little hope of there being just 1 or 2 of complete graphs.  This is a characteristic in the NFL too, in which teams play only 16 games per season, but unlike college football, there are only 32 NFL teams.  Take a look at the graph of college football from the 2012 season:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
   &lt;a href=&quot;/images/cfb_network_cluster.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;60%&quot; src=&quot;/images/cfb_network_cluster.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
   &lt;figcaption&gt; The network of college football.  Teams are nodes, and edges are games between teams.  The six power conferences are clustered together, and the gray circle of teams in the middle are the non-power conference teams. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are six so-called &lt;em&gt;power&lt;/em&gt; conferences which are well-connected within themselves, and are represented by the six clustered groups of teams around the perimeter of the above picture.  Outside of these six conferences, there are the remaining 50% of college football teams that are either independent or in lesser conferences; these teams are represented in gray in the inner circle.  There are few games between power conferences, but lots of games between power and non-power conference teams (these are the edges connecting vertices in the inner circle to one of the outer circle teams).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ranking-teams-with-pagerank&quot;&gt;Ranking teams with PageRank&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because there no large, complete sub-graphs in the college football network, ranking college football teams is a non-trivial task.  Until recently, there was a selection procedure that used computer models to determine rankings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google’s PageRank is an algorithm developed by Google co-founder Larry Page for ranking webpages for importance.  In Page’s original formulation, the internet was modeled as a directed graph with pages as nodes and edges being links from one page to another.  This graph was represented with an adjacency matrix &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;A&lt;/script&gt;, whose entries &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;a_{ij}&lt;/script&gt; are givn by&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;a_{ij} = \textrm{edge weight from node } i \textrm{ to node } j&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PageRank algorithm works (roughly) by using power iteration to obtain the dominant eigenvector &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;v&lt;/script&gt; of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;A&lt;/script&gt;.  The value of entry &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;v_i&lt;/script&gt; in the eigenvector represents the PageRank of node &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;i&lt;/script&gt;.  PageRank includes some extra steps to treat edge cases in which the graph is disconnected or there are closed loops, but this is the basic idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can apply PageRank to rank college football teams too.  Again, the teams are the nodes &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;v_i&lt;/script&gt;, the edges are the games between them, and the edge weights are the score differential; the edges point from the winning team to the losing team.  Like anything else reasonably famous, these is a Python package to compute pageranks of directed, weighted graphs called networkx.  I used Python/networkx along with data from the 2014 college football season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, let’s just see how PageRank does with the 2015 season.  Here is the ranking of the top-10 teams of the 2015 college football season according to PageRank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1. Ohio St.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2. Oregon&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3. Baylor&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4. Mississippi&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5. Georgia&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6. Georgia Tech&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7. Virginia Tech&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8. Alabama&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9. Texas Christian&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10. Missouri&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are somewhat reasonable results; the national champion and runner-up are correctly ranked at #1 and #2.  The rest of the teams are at least all pretty good.  Florida St. is not ranked in the top ten even though they were ranked as the #3 team before the playoffs, but that was a questionable ranking and Florida St. was beaten soundly in their first playoff game.  All-in-all, this seems to produce reasonable results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;adding-noise-to-the-network&quot;&gt;Adding noise to the network&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question I want to ask is, &lt;em&gt;How sensitive is PageRank to noise&lt;/em&gt;?  In this context, noise can be interpreted as luck, and can be modeled as adding to the score differential a zero-mean Gaussian random variable with some variance.  In math, this means that I’ll modify the non-zero entries of the adjacency matrix &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;A&lt;/script&gt; and create a new matrix &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\tilde{A}&lt;/script&gt; whose entries are defined as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\tilde{a}_{ij} =a_{ij} + N(0,\sigma)&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where-ever &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;A&lt;/script&gt; is non-zero.  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;N(0,\sigma)&lt;/script&gt; is a zero-mean Gaussian random variable with standard deviation &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\sigma&lt;/script&gt;.  In my interpretation, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\sigma&lt;/script&gt; represents how much we think luck matters.  Some possible choices of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\sigma&lt;/script&gt; are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\sigma = 0&lt;/script&gt;: this means we think the scores represent perfectly who the better team was and by how much.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\sigma = 3&lt;/script&gt;: this means we think that luck matters about a field goal’s worth of points.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\sigma = 6&lt;/script&gt;: this means we think that luck matters about a touchdown’s worth of points.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally many other choices are possible, but I wanted to try these three since they have clear interpretations in the context of college football.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, and most importantly, I wanted to  make sure I wasn’t monkeying around too much with the data by adding noise everywhere in the college football network.  So, I only added the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;N(0,\sigma)&lt;/script&gt; noise term to games between bad teams.  Any games that included teams ranked roughly in the top-25 of PageRank scores were not modified at all.  My goal was to see if adding noise to &lt;em&gt;unimportant&lt;/em&gt; games (those between bad teams) would affect the rankings of good teams.  Basically what I’m saying is that no one really cares about the outcome of Idaho St. vs. Bowling Green (sorry Vandals and Falcons), and so adding noise to those games should, in principle, not affect the top-10 teams at all.  This turns out to not be true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the time, as you would expect, when you add noise to teams outside of the top 25, you see no difference in the top-10 rankings; they’re the same ones I posted above.  But every once in a while, the top-10 will change, and even less frequenctly, the &lt;em&gt;number&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; ranked team will change!  In the following table I’ve summarized the results of simulating 1000 trials of random noise with &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\sigma = 0,3&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;6&lt;/script&gt;.  I picked out the resulting subset of trials in which Oregon was ranked higher than Ohio St., and have listed the the results for the top-10 teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\sigma = 0&lt;/script&gt; (1000/1000 times)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\sigma = 3&lt;/script&gt; (1/1000 times)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\sigma = 6&lt;/script&gt; (12/1000 times)&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;1. Ohio St.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;1. Oregon&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;1. Oregon&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;2. Oregon&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;2. Ohio St.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;2. Ohio St.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;3. Baylor&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;3. Baylor&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;3. Baylor&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;4. Mississippi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;4. Mississippi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;4. Georgia&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;5. Georgia&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;5. Georgia&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;5. Mississippi&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;6. Georgia Tech&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;6. Georgia Tech&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;6. Georgia Tech&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;7. Virginia Tech&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;7. Virginia Tech&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;7. Virginia Tech&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;8. Alabama&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;8. Alabama&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;8. Alabama&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;9. Texas Christian&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;9. Texas Christian&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;9. Texas Christian&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;10. Missouri&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;10. Missouri&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;10. Missouri&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a weird thing that is happening, and sort of shows the limitation of PageRank as it pertains to the college football network.  First, we (as college football fans) care a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; about who is #1 and who is #2.  PageRank doesn’t care about this as much; it just wants to make sure that good teams are given good scores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, the college football network has a very peculiar characteristic in that most paths from high-ranked nodes to other high-ranked nodes travel through the set of low-ranked nodes.  This means that information flows from good teams to good teams through bad teams and the unimportant games between them.  When I add noise to those unimportant games, it can alter the way the paths connect good teams to good teams.  This manifests as changing the PageRank of teams whose games I did not touch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would be curious to see what would happen if I did a similar PageRank + noise experiment with other sports leagues, especially those, like the NBA, whose graphs are complete.  Would the PageRank then be more resilient to noise?&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/football/google-pagerank-and-ncaa-football/&quot;&gt;Google PageRank, NCAA Football, and Luck&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Sumedh Joshi at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Sumedh Joshi&lt;/a&gt; on July 03, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[How Good Is the Average Golfer?]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/golf/how-good-is-the-average-golfer/" />
  <id>/golf/how-good-is-the-average-golfer</id>
  <published>2015-07-02T23:47:09-05:00</published>
  <updated>2015-07-02T23:47:09-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Sumedh Joshi</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>sumedh.m.joshi@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;figure&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;instagram-media&quot; data-instgrm-captioned=&quot;&quot; data-instgrm-version=&quot;4&quot; style=&quot; background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:358px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;padding:8px;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:#F8F8F8; line-height:0; margin-top:40px; padding:50% 0; text-align:center; width:100%;&quot;&gt; &lt;div style=&quot; background:url(data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAACwAAAAsCAMAAAApWqozAAAAGFBMVEUiIiI9PT0eHh4gIB4hIBkcHBwcHBwcHBydr+JQAAAACHRSTlMABA4YHyQsM5jtaMwAAADfSURBVDjL7ZVBEgMhCAQBAf//42xcNbpAqakcM0ftUmFAAIBE81IqBJdS3lS6zs3bIpB9WED3YYXFPmHRfT8sgyrCP1x8uEUxLMzNWElFOYCV6mHWWwMzdPEKHlhLw7NWJqkHc4uIZphavDzA2JPzUDsBZziNae2S6owH8xPmX8G7zzgKEOPUoYHvGz1TBCxMkd3kwNVbU0gKHkx+iZILf77IofhrY1nYFnB/lQPb79drWOyJVa/DAvg9B/rLB4cC+Nqgdz/TvBbBnr6GBReqn/nRmDgaQEej7WhonozjF+Y2I/fZou/qAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC); display:block; height:44px; margin:0 auto -44px; position:relative; top:-22px; width:44px;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;p style=&quot; margin:8px 0 0 0; padding:0 4px;&quot;&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://instagram.com/p/4pIxyolf1m/&quot; style=&quot; color:#000; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none; word-wrap:break-word;&quot; target=&quot;_top&quot;&gt;Hole 15 Colo Vista. Like 40 yards downhill.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p style=&quot; color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;&quot;&gt;A photo posted by sumedh (@ithacaisnotthatgreat) on &lt;time style=&quot; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px;&quot; datetime=&quot;2015-07-02T17:50:39+00:00&quot;&gt;Jul 2, 2015 at 10:50am PDT&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; defer=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.instagram.com/en_US/embeds.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
   &lt;figcaption&gt; Hole #15 at Cola Vista Golf Course in Bastrop, TX. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;handicap&quot;&gt;Handicap&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A golfer’s skill is often measured by a &lt;em&gt;handicap&lt;/em&gt;, which is the average number of strokes over par that it takes for the golfer to complete a course.  According to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.usga.org/Handicapping/handicap-index-statistics/mens-handicap-index-statistics-d24e6096.html&quot;&gt;USGA&lt;/a&gt;, over half of all golfers are a +13.0 handicap or better, and almost 80% of all golfers are a +18.0 or better.  This seems to suggest that the vast majority of golfers take about an extra stroke over par per hole. If you have never played golf, let me just say, shooting a +18 is not easy to do, and is not at all indicative of the average golfer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the way a handicap is measured is incredibly &lt;a href=&quot;http://usga.org/Rule-Books/Handicap-System-Manual/Rule-10/&quot;&gt;complicated&lt;/a&gt;, but I will try to summarize.  To compute your handicap, you first pick out the best few recent rounds of golf you’ve played.  Then, you throw out the best scores among those (usually about half of your rounds get tossed out), and compute the average score of the remaining rounds.  That average score is your handicap.  Because you’re forced to discard your best few scores, to have a good handicap you either have to be consistently good, or be inconsistent and &lt;em&gt;play&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;of&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;golf&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with using handicap to measure the average golfer is that most bad golfers don’t even know their handicap, if they keep score (accurately) at all.  And even if they did keep their score (accurately), they probably are not paying to register it with the USGA.  So essentially, nobody really knows how bad the average golfer is.  I would hazard a guess (based on my playing experience) that the average golfer that plays enough to have a handicap probably shoots in the high 110’s which is a +45 handicap.  The distribution of scores is certainly very asymmetrical and likely has a heavy tail, populated with folks like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.golfchannel.com/media/remembering-angelo-worst-avid-golfer/&quot;&gt;Angelo Spagnolo&lt;/a&gt; who owns the distinction of being the world’s worst avid golfer with a handicap rating of +56, and once shooting over a 200 on a professional PGA course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-handicap&quot;&gt;My Handicap&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve only played about 20 or so rounds of golf in my life, and most of those I either didn’t keep score, didn’t finish, or don’t have my scorecard.  But, I do have scores for the last five rounds I’ve played.  It’s not pretty:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Course&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Score&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Greatwood&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;141&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Morris Williams&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;129&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;BlackHawk&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;110&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Bluebonnet Hill&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;104&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;Colo Vista&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;125&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, by the letter of the handicap rule, my handicap would be based on entirely my worst score, Greatwood, resulting in a course-adjusted score of about 140.  To put that into perspective, it means that I take about twice as many strokes per hole as allowed!  Greatwood is a tough course, especially for beginners (its &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slope_rating&quot;&gt;slope rating&lt;/a&gt; is 145, the highest of any course I’ve played), but it’s not &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; tough; I am just a bad golfer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, and this is my point, handicap rating views me really unfavorably for the same reasons it views all beginning golfers unfavorably:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I am inconsistent:&lt;/strong&gt; There is a spread of 37 strokes between my best and my worst scores, that’s like 9 holes of golf!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I haven’t played much:&lt;/strong&gt; And worse, I have not played enough golf to offset my bad outliers with good outliers.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I am not good at golf:&lt;/strong&gt; …&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(possibly not in that order).  So, to beginning golfers everywhere: ignore the handicap rating entirely; we’re not even playing golf yet.&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/golf/how-good-is-the-average-golfer/&quot;&gt;How Good Is the Average Golfer?&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Sumedh Joshi at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Sumedh Joshi&lt;/a&gt; on July 02, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Setting Up a Github Repository for Hosting on Github Pages]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/meta/setting-up-a-github-repository-for-hosting-on-github-pages/" />
  <id>/meta/setting-up-a-github-repository-for-hosting-on-github-pages</id>
  <published>2015-07-02T20:21:01-05:00</published>
  <updated>2015-07-02T20:21:01-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Sumedh Joshi</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>sumedh.m.joshi@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Most of this was taken from the helpful guide on Github’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/&quot;&gt;own webpage&lt;/a&gt;.  It is incredibly easy to host
pages on Github so long as you have a basic working knowledge of version control (I had never used Git before, but I know Mercurial
and that was enough).  Here are the steps I took.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;steps&quot;&gt;Steps&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create a Github account with username &lt;em&gt;sumedhjoshi&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create a repository called &lt;em&gt;sumedhjoshi.github.io&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On your local machine, clone the git repository you just made:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;git clone sumedhjoshi.github.io&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Copy the Jekyll directory tree that contains your Jekyll webpage into this folder.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;cd &lt;/span&gt;sumedhjoshi.github.io
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;cp -R /path/to/jekyll/folder .&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add all the Jekyll files to your repository, and commit and push the changes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;git add --all
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;git commit
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;git push&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Navigate to &lt;em&gt;sumedhjoshi.github.io&lt;/em&gt;, Github Pages will automatically generate your webpage and serve it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All future updates can be made locally and pushed with git to &lt;em&gt;sumedhjoshi.github.io&lt;/em&gt; and they will take effect immediately!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/meta/setting-up-a-github-repository-for-hosting-on-github-pages/&quot;&gt;Setting Up a Github Repository for Hosting on Github Pages&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Sumedh Joshi at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Sumedh Joshi&lt;/a&gt; on July 02, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Setting Up MathJax LaTeX Support]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/meta/setup/setting-up-mathjax-latex-support/" />
  <id>/meta/setup/setting-up-mathjax-latex-support</id>
  <published>2015-06-27T17:31:33-05:00</published>
  <updated>2015-06-27T17:31:33-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Sumedh Joshi</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>sumedh.m.joshi@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;This is easy, just add the following snippet into the body of the _layout/post.html:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot; data-lang=&quot;html&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;script &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;type=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;text/javascript&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;src=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;http://cdn.mathjax.org/mathjax/latest/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will add MathJax support to all posts. To typset LaTeX, just surround any LaTeX syntax with two dollar signs, like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-latex&quot; data-lang=&quot;latex&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sb&quot;&gt;$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;u,v&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;\int&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;_&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;\Omega&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt; u&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt; v^&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt; d&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;\Omega&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;$$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;to produce&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;(u,v) = \int_\Omega u(x) v^*(x) d\Omega&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you also want MathJax support on website pages, add the same code snippet to _layout/page.html.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/meta/setup/setting-up-mathjax-latex-support/&quot;&gt;Setting Up MathJax LaTeX Support&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Sumedh Joshi at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Sumedh Joshi&lt;/a&gt; on June 27, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Setting Up Disqus]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/meta/setup/setting-up-disqus/" />
  <id>/meta/setup/setting-up-disqus</id>
  <published>2015-06-27T14:45:07-05:00</published>
  <updated>2015-06-27T14:45:07-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Sumedh Joshi</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>sumedh.m.joshi@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;I basically followed the very clear instructions set up on &lt;a href=&quot;http://joshualande.com/jekyll-github-pages-poole/&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; blog post.
There are instructions there for setting up a GitHub hosting account (which is free, for some reason, if you’re using Jekyll), setting up a domain name to point to the GitHub host, setting up Google Analytics, and setting up the Disqus commenting system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;disqus&quot;&gt;Disqus&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Make a &lt;a href=&quot;www.disqus.com&quot;&gt;Disqus&lt;/a&gt; account.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Create a short-name by registering &lt;a href=&quot;https://disqus.com/admin/create/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Enable Disqus by setting the disqus-shortname variable in the Jekyll config file.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Set “comments: true” in the YAML front matter of any post that you want commenting enabled on!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/meta/setup/setting-up-disqus/&quot;&gt;Setting Up Disqus&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Sumedh Joshi at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Sumedh Joshi&lt;/a&gt; on June 27, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[How I Set Up This Site]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="/programming/meta/notes/how-i-set-up-this-site/" />
  <id>/programming/meta/notes/how-i-set-up-this-site</id>
  <published>2015-06-27T01:47:07-05:00</published>
  <updated>2015-06-27T01:47:07-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Sumedh Joshi</name>
    <uri></uri>
    <email>sumedh.m.joshi@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Upgraded Ruby to version 2.1.1 to be compatible with clang.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Downloaded and installed Jekyll from http://jekyllrb.com/.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Downloaded and installed the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mmistakes/minimal-mistakes/blob/master/theme-setup/index.md&quot;&gt;Minimial Mistakes&lt;/a&gt; theme.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Modified the images in the /images folder to be smaller in height to save vertical real estate (first installed imagemagick):&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; $ mogrify -crop 100%x40%+0+0 sample-image-?.jpg
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Installed the octopress gem:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; $ gem install octopress
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Made this post with octopress:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; $ octopress new post &quot;How I Set Up This Site&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/programming/meta/notes/how-i-set-up-this-site/&quot;&gt;How I Set Up This Site&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Sumedh Joshi at &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Sumedh Joshi&lt;/a&gt; on June 27, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>

</feed>
